A Guide to the Richard Campbell Manson, MD Papers 1934-1967
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Dr. Richard Campbell Manson Papers 1934-1967
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
2001/Nov/5
2 boxes
Dr. Richard Campbell Manson
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Collection was donated to the Department by Richard C. Manson, Jr.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Richard Campbell Manson was born in Richmond on October 17, 1908. He graduated from Randolph-Macon College, in 1930. Dr. Manson graduated from the Medical College of Virginia in 1934. Dr. Manson was a veteran of World War II; he joined the 45th General Hospital as chief dermatologist. He rose to the rank of major and was awarded the Bronze Star.
Dr. Manson had a decorated professional career; he served as president of the Richmond Academy of medicine, the Virginia Dermatological Society, and the Southeastern Dermatological Society. Dr. Manson was the founding member of the Richmond Dermatological Society and the Virginia Dermatology Society. In 1947, Dr. Manson was certified by the American Board of Dermatology and Syphilology, he also was a fellow member of the American Academy of Dermatology. For fifty years Dr. Manson served on the adjunct faculty at MCV, in 1962 he was appointed clinical professor of dermatology.
Dr. Manson affectionately known as "Hump" had numerous interests outside of his career, he served as president of the Richmond Chapter of the MCV Alumni Association. Dr. Manson was an avid golfer, and played the saxophone as an amateur and semiprofessional. He took great pleasure in arranging reunions for the class of 1934.
Scope and Content Information
The majority of the Manson papers are devoted to his affiliation with the 45th during and after the war.
Series I contains mostly notes from meetings, memos and correspondences from members of t he 45th. The topics usually discussed were planning for annual meeting, dinner, and reunion.
Series II consists of professional documents concerning Dr. Manson's affiliation with the Richmond Dermatological Society, Virginia Dermatological Society, and the Southeastern Dermatological Society. There is also a letter to Dr. Manson's son concerning his passing, along with a brief description on Dr. Manson's Medical practice.
Arrangement
Materials arranged in chronological order
Contents List
- Forty-fifth General Hospital 1942-1967
  - Reports on Venereal Diseases from the War Department 1942 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Memos 45th 1945 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - 3 Minutes on Meetings of the 45th 1946 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Minutes on Stoneburner Fund (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Memos on the Stoneburner Fund (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Memos on Possible Facilitators 1948 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Mailing list of the 45th (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Minutes of the Meeting for the 45th 1949 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Minutes of the Meeting for the 45th 1950 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Correspondence and Minutes 1951 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Correspondence 1952 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - RSVP for Annual Meeting 1956 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Memos 1957 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Memos 1958-1960 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Announcements 1961 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Correspondence 1962 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Memos 1963 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - Memos-Catering Receipts 1967 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - Memos and Whiskey List (Box-folder 1.19)
  - Bank Statements (Box-folder 1.20)
  - 45th Bank Book, Statements, and Returned Checks (Box-folder 1.21)
  - Photos (Box-folder 1.22)
- Dermatological Society
  - Memos Alumni Association/Class Reunion 1934 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Memos Medical Society (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Virginia Dermatological Society (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Virginia Dermatological Society (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Virginia Dermatological Society (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Richmond Dermatological Society Constitution (Box-folder 2.6)
  - International Congress of Dermatology Conference in Tokyo (Box-folder 2.7)
  - Richmond Academy of Medicine (Box-folder 2.8)
  - Richmond Academy of Medicine (Box-folder 2.9)
  - Bills (Box-folder 2.10)
  - Scarb (Box-folder 2.11)
  - Scarb and Randolph-Macon College Bulletin (Box-folder 2.12)
  - Memos (Box-folder 2.13)
  - Brief History/Biography (Box-folder 2.14)
  - Medicovan (Box-folder 2.15)